Good morning, חודש טוב. Chodesh Tov.
We pick up at the bottom of today's דף, daf, צדי ב,
Tzadi Bet, 92, we pick up at the bottom of צדי א
עמוד ב Tzadi Aleph amud Bet and we are dealing again with
this issue about, we finished the question about which things come first
and then we got into this whole point about can you give
a דבר davar of שמן, shemen, a just like a free will
offering of oil, and if so, so that's a debate in the
משנה, Mishnah, רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי טרפון. Rabbi Tarfon. And
within רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon the question is, so what is it
like? Is it like a מנחה mincha that you do a קומץ
kometz and the כהנים kohanim eat the
rest or is
it like an עולה olah essentially in which it's all burnt or
like נסכים nesachim in which they are and all sort of poured
on the מזבח? mizbe'ach? And to some degree the גמרא Gemara tied
that into the debate of whether it, within רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon
here, of whether it's one לוג log or three לוג. log. If
it's one לוג log it's based on the model of the מנחה
mincha where you had one לוג log of oil. If it's three
לוג log it's based on the model of the wine, the מנחת
נסכים minchat nesachim which according to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva also you
could bring that as a separate קרבן, korban, and that would be
poured all of it on the altar, except not on the fire,
it would go down a funnel. So here too if that's your
approach is to learn from the wine, you would say three לוג
log and then you would also say though presumably that it all
goes on the fire. Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara picks up
with the following.
אמר שמואל. Amar Shmuel. So now it is about 10 lines from
the bottom, asterisk in the middle of the
line, starts with איתניא תניא, it tanya tanya, then there's another asterisk.
אמר שמואל המתנדב יין מביא ומזיפו גבי אישים. Amar Shmuel Hamitnadev yayin
mevi umazippo gabei ishim. So now שמואל Shmuel says something about the
wine. Until now all of the תנאים Tanaim seemed to be saying
that if you do the wine, you pour it down the ספלים,
sfalim, you pour it down the funnels, which is what you do
with the wine of the מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim and what you
do with the water on סוכות. Sukkot. But שמואל Shmuel says if
you do a separate קרבן korban of wine, you would actually burn
it on the fire, the same way you would do the oil
on the fire.
מאי טעמא? Mai ta'ama? What's the reason? אמר קרא Amar kra the
verse says ויין תקריב לנסך חצי ההין
אשה ריח ניחוח להשם. V'yayin takriv lanesekh chatzi hahin isheh rei'ach nichoach
l'Hashem. Wine should be for
a libation half of a הין, hin, it should be a burnt
offering. So you could say the burnt offering is sort of going
maybe on the מנחה mincha part of it or whatever on the
whole קרבן, korban, but the פשט pshat is, it uses the word
אשה, isheh, a something on the fire for the wine that comes
with the קרבנות. korbanot. So now the interesting thing though is that
he's not disagreeing with the idea that the יין נסכים yein nesakhim
which is the פשט pshat of the פסוקים psukim goes down the
ספלים. sfalim. Everybody agreed that there were these funnels, you know, and
that there were the whole things that they dug underneath the מזבח,
mizbe'ach, you know, the whole sort of what do you call it?
Cavern or whatever in which the wine went down. That everybody agrees
to. But to the degree that we learn also this from these
פסוקים psukim from the word אזרח ezrach or wherever we learn it
that there's an independent קרבן korban of wine, then that we're going
to read the פסוק pasuk אשה isheh literally and that gets put
on the fire. So now the גמרא Gemara has the following question.
Everyone agrees if you נתנדב nitnadev oil separately it goes on the
אש? esh?
Right, whether it's the whole thing or the קומץ kometz or whatever.
Right. The only question is with the wine.
Right. And the wine, right, the simple sense was, I mean the
גמרא Gemara started, יין כדברי רבי עקיבא לספלים. yayin k'divrei Rabbi Akiva
l'sfalim. Okay, so it's quite interesting you know that שמואל Shmuel seems
to be arguing on Tannaitic positions. He's getting it from a פסוק,
pasuk, but even that פסוק pasuk isn't true about the פשט pshat
of the פסוק, pasuk, I mean about the original context of the
פסוק, pasuk, it's not true about the wine that comes as a
מנחת נסכים minchat nesachim together with a קרבן, korban, but he is
going to keep the פשט pshat of that פסוק pasuk ואשה v'isheh
for wine that comes by itself. So the גמרא Gemara says והא
קא מכבי כיבויי. V'ha ka mechabi chibuyei.
I don't understand, how can you do that? You throw oil on
the fire, you know, you're just going to add fuel.
Fuel to the fire? Right, exactly, that's exactly it. Adding fuel to
the fire. Oil burns but it might burn, but it's still a
liquid that is going to actually do some extinguishing of the fire.
And we learned that the point about, the fact that the fire
says, right,
that it has to be אש תמיד תוקד על המזבח esh tamid
tukad al hamizbe'ach is that a constant fire, that we learn from
that implicitly that it's prohibited to extinguish the fire. So how are
you allowed to put the wine on? You're going to extinguish the
fire. והא קא מכבי? V'ha ka mechabi? Aren't you extinguishing it? So
the גמרא's Gemara answer is כיבויי במקצת לא שמי כיבוי. Chibuyei b'miktzat
lo shmei chibui. No, the issue is, you know, that it should
be right, you know, it should be a תמיד, tamid, the fire
should constantly be there. It doesn't mean that you can't extinguish some
of the fire, as long as there's still some fire there you're
okay, as long as there's an אש תמיד. esh tamid. So the
גמרא Gemara says איני? Eini? Is that really, I mean it makes
sense in terms of the פסוק, pasuk, but let's see if that's
true. והא אמר רב נחמן אמר רבה בר אבוה המוריד גחלת מעל
גבי המזבח וכיבה
חייב. V'ha amar Rav Nachman amar Rabbah bar Avuha Hamorid gachelet mei-al
gabei hamizbe'ach v'chibah chayav. If you took one coal off the מזבח
mizbe'ach and you extinguished it, you're חייב. chayav. So first of all
that's pretty interesting. why do you have to be מוריד גחלת? morid
gachelet? Maybe if once you're מוריד morid it, it's not such a
problem because then it's no longer part of the fire of the
מזבח. mizbe'ach. And even there, I mean תוספות Tosafot has a little
bit of that question, why דווקא davka גחלת? gachelet? What if it
fell off, etc. Why don't we say נעשית מצותו na'asis mitzvaso if
it's already a גחלת? gachelet? Why is there still a prohibition? But
anyway, here it says
like even one coal is a problem. It's not that only if
you extinguish the whole fire. So the גמרא Gemara says, so
the גמרא Gemara says דליכא אלא האי. de-leika ela hai. No no
no, we're talking about a scenario where that coal was the only
fire on the מזבח. mizbe'ach. So by extinguishing it, you were extinguishing
all the fire. I assume that's not what you had in mind,
Michael. איבעית אימא, I-ba'is eima, if you want I can tell you
כיבויי דמצווה שאני, kibuy de-mitzvah shani, right, which is fine, you're right,
even extinguishing a little bit is a problem when you're doing it
for no purpose. But if it's in the context of what the
תורה Torah tells you to do, let's say what you did is
you actually threw the entrails on the fire, you know, and right,
depending on which part of the fire you hit, right, it could
extinguish a coal, right, if it you know, so nevertheless that's the
מצווה. mitzvah. So in the context of putting the stuff that you're
commanded to offer on the fire on the fire, you're not concerned
about maybe it'll cause a little piece of the fire to go
out and you know, presumably as long as some of the fire
still remains.
That was my first thinking too but the other answer you had
said it depends if you know if it's on the מזבח mizbe'ach
it's like all connected so you're not really like you know unless
you specifically take a coal and you focus on it independently.
Could be, could be, yeah.
The purpose of the coal was to burn these things. So I
mean you know it's not the purpose is not to have coals
on the altar, it is to have the fire to burn things.
So I mean if that's what they're doing they're functioning that way
you're not actually are you actually like
extinguishing?
Yeah. Well you are, I mean you could sort of say you
have to always do it in a way in which you're putting
it on the top of the fire that there's a strong enough
fire that it's always going to just you know burn and not
ex- you know and and not put out a piece of it.
But yeah, I mean essentially what you're saying is what the גמרא
Gemara means when it says מצווה שאני, mitzvah shani, that this is
all part of like what you're supposed to be doing. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay,
so
where are we? איבעית אימא I-ba'is eima fine. תא שמע, Ta shema,
come and hear, תנא רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Tana Rabbi Eliezer ben
Yaakov, כלפי שניתנה תורה לתרום, kelapei she-nitnah Torah litrom, יכול יכבה. yachol
yechabe.
We got a ברייתא braita that Rabbi Eliezer ben Yaakov says, once
the תורה Torah tells you to do תרומת הדשן, Trumas Ha-Deshen, I
might think that maybe you're allowed in the process of removing the
ashes to extinguish some of the flames, תם יתרום. tam yitrom. אמרת
לא יכבה. amarta lo yechabe. No, the תורה Torah says don't extinguish.
It doesn't say don't extinguish, it says אש תמיד, eish tamid, but
anyway the point is you're not allowed to extinguish while you're in
the process of doing תרומת הדשן. Trumas Ha-Deshen. Why isn't that כיבויי
דמצווה? kibuy de-mitzvah? I mean you're doing it in the context of
a מצווה. mitzvah. Now again there's a difference in terms of what
type of מצווה. mitzvah. There, you know, it's sort of like what
David was saying,
it's like incidental to the מצווה. mitzvah. Like focus on a part
where it's already turned into ashes, right, as opposed to you're supposed
to put something on the fire. If in the process of putting
it on the fire it caused something to extinguish, you had no
choice. What you were supposed to do was put it on the
fire, okay? Whereas here, it's like nobody's telling you you have to
take the ashes from a part in which you know in which
there's still a burning fire. Anyway the גמרא Gemara says like this,
anyway that's the question. שאני התם אפשר דיתיב ונטר. shani hasam efshar
de-yasiv ve-natar. There, which is you could say it's what the answer
is, it says there if the only part, meaning the גמרא Gemara
imagines that maybe what it's telling you is like let's say there's
no other place to get the ashes from. You go up and
the only place you know to get the ashes is in the
middle of a place where the fire is still burning. Or let's
say whatever for some bizarre reason it would be hard to imagine
the scenario but there are no ashes yet on the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
And there's a coal. You know, why don't you do it's like
when you're done with a campfire, what do you do? You know
you stomp it out or whatever. So you go up to the
top of the מזבח, mizbe'ach, there are no ashes, why don't you
just stomp out the the coal, turn it into ashes and take
it? Okay, so there that would be actually a better
comparison to the case of putting the thing on the fire. You
need to be doing that in order to be getting the ashes.
So you tell me you need to put something on the coal
in order to offer it and that might extinguish. Well here if
there's no other ashes, you need to be doing this in order
to get the ashes. So the גמרא Gemara says yeah but there
you got a choice. There you could just sit and wait until
the fire goes out, right, so come back later, okay,
whereas here, you know you've got to put the the wine on
the fire. So there's no getting around the fact that to do
this מצווה mitzvah is going to lead to a certain degree of
extinction.
Wait so are we talking about the case that the only time
you can...
That seems to be the גמרא's Gemara point because it could have
just said why don't you just get the ashes somewhere else. It
says why don't you just wait.
So אין הכי נמי,
ein hachi nami, we accept the idea that the scenario here is
telling you you're not allowed to extinguish it even if there's no
other way to get ashes. But it's still different than our case
because there there's alternatives, you can wait, whereas in our case the
only thing you can do is put it on the fire and
if that necessarily leads to extinguishing, so be it.
Would they then delay the תמיד Tamid until it goes out?
Yeah I mean that's an interesting question about what... What would you
do if you couldn't do the תרומת הדשן Trumas Hadeshen the first
thing? Yeah, so I don't know the answer to that. That's a
good question. Look, the other question could be, let's say according to
this, I could say that if I put it on enough on
a, maybe the גמרא Gemara understands that the, you know, wine even
if it's a raging fire will do a certain amount of extinguishing.
I don't know, I'm assuming. But you know, the scenario I gave
before, which is that you've got a an entrails and if you
put it on the fire, it's actually, you know, you got a
low flame here and you got a coal and it's going to
put that out. Maybe the גמרא Gemara would say that's not allowed.
You gotta wait until the fire gets bigger or find a better
place on the fire, right? So it's not exactly clear here. The
גמרא Gemara might be sort of saying it's not just that it's
מצוה, mitzvah, it's מצוה mitzvah and you have no other choice. So
by the תרומת הדשן, Trumas Hadeshen, you have a choice. Okay, maybe
in my example about, you know, don't put the the entrails on
a low coal that it's going to extinguish. You know, you have
a choice, find a higher flame, but with the wine you don't
have a choice. Yes.
Is there a minimum שיעור shiur for the amount of ashes to
need to be removed for תרומת הדשן? Trumas Hadeshen?
Yeah, I mean, you know, it's like one scoop's worth or whatever.
Because it's not a huge amount of ashes given...
Right, I understand. You have to imagine the scenario. Anyway, so the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay. תא
שמע, Ta shma, יין כדברי רבי עקיבא לספלים. yayin k'divrei Rebbe Akiva
l'sfalim. We got a ברייתא, Braisa, Shmuel, it sounds very nice, but
you know, Shmuel, I forgot, I don't know and you got a
פסוק, pasuk, but Shmuel, I don't know if anybody told you you're
an אמורא Amora here and we've got some תנאים Tannaim that say
that for Rebbe Akiva it goes down the funnel. שמן כדברי רבי
טרפון לאשים. Shemen k'divrei Rebbe Tarfon l'ishim. ועוד תניא, Ve-od tanya, we
learned another ברייתא, Braisa,
יין נסך
לספלים. yayin nesech l'sfalim. It goes down the, you know, it goes
down the funnels. או אינו אלא לאשים, O eino ela l'ishim,
maybe it should go on the flame. אמרת לא יכבה. Amarta lo
yechabeh. And the ברייתא Braisa actually teaches like, no, that exactly, we
had the same הוה אמינא, hava amina, put it on the fire,
but the ברייתא Braisa teaches that no, because that would be a
violation of extinguishing the fire. So therefore, Shmuel, how can you say
you can actually do this? You got ברייתות Braisas that go against
you. So the גמרא Gemara says, לא קשיא הא רבי יהודה הא
רבי שמעון. lo kashya ha Rebbe Yehuda ha Rebbe Shimon. It's a
debate of רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. Now
it's not exactly הא רבי שמעון ha Rebbe Shimon because what it's
really saying is Shmuel saying I hold like רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon.
All of these ברייתות Braisas that teach that you don't put it
on the fire basically says look, they've got a problem because the
פסוק pasuk says אשי ריח ניחוח להשם. ishei reiach nichoach l'Hashem. So
all of these ברייתות, Braisas, now of course as we pointed out,
that's not, we don't read it that way when you're talking about
the actual explicit פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, which is about
the wine that gets put on as a מנחת נסכים. minchas nesachim.
But okay, but he says, it does say fire. So the, so
what I'm saying is פשט, pshat, says Shmuel, that something's got to
go on the fire of this wine, at least some version of
this wine. So the ברייתות Braisas that say not that way, there's
something pushing them to not read the פסוק pasuk to say that
it goes on the fire. You know what's pushing them to say
that? Exactly your problem, that it's going to extinguish a flame. So,
but why am I not bothered? Well, says Shmuel, it's a question
about רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון. Rebbe Shimon. רבי יהודה
Rebbe Yehuda and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon debate in שבת, Shabbat, and
it's a generally assumed, and here's an important גמרא Gemara in that
debate, it's assumed that it's not limited to שבת, Shabbat, the question
about אינו מתכוין. eino miskavein. If you do something that is not
intentional, okay, is that considered a violation or not? So if I
go ahead, right, the classic example is, I'm going to drag a
bench across a flower bed on שבת, Shabbat, and my intention is
to get it to the other side, but the process is it's
going to make a furrow, okay, so have I violated שבת? Shabbat?
So, now why don't you just say yes, you might be a
שוגג shogeg but you violated שבת. Shabbat. Well, if I know it's
going to create the furrow, okay, then you could sort of say
that's, you know, that gets to questions about אינו מתכוין eino miskavein
and פסיק רישא, psik reisha, and then maybe we could all like
assume that you're yes, it is a violation. But let's say it's
not definitely going to create the furrow. So, רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda
and רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon would say, go ahead and do it.
Your act is basically dragging a bench. You know, if it creates
a furrow, it's incidental and unintended. And we don't say after the
fact, aha, you created the furrow, see that you were מחלל שבת,
mechallel Shabbat, okay, you were a שוגג shogeg but whatever. Even if
it winds up that after the fact you've created that furrow, since
it was A incidental and B not a necessary consequence, it's like
you didn't do it. You're not connected to it and even if
it happens, it's not your responsibility. Whereas רבי יהודה Rebbe Yehuda says,
look, if you're lucky enough to drag it across the bench and
to drag it across the flower bed and a furrow didn't get
made, you wouldn't violate. I'm not saying you violate by the fact
that you open yourself to that risk. You but if it works
out that you did create it, then I would say, aha, you
were violated שבת Shabbat and maybe you weren't intentional, maybe you were
שוגג shogeg but you violated שבת Shabbat so don't drag that bench
because if it winds up that it made the furrow, you cannot
be free of responsibility. So basically what they are debating is if
something is going to happen incidental to what I'm intending and again,
this is the point about that gets added in the גמרא. Gemara.
It's not a פסיק רישא, psik reisha, it's not a necessary consequence,
then
רבי שמעון Rebbe Shimon So שמואל Shmuel says, so I say like
רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. So sprinkle it on the fire, okay, it
won't necessarily put out the fire. We'll get to that in a
minute. If it happens, you weren't trying to do it, it wasn't
necessarily going to happen, you won't have violated. The ברייתות baraitot that
say that the wine goes down the funnels and are not reading
the פסוקים pesukim their literal way of אשה ריח ניחוח לה', isheh
reiach nichoach l'Adonai, what's forcing them not to read the פסוקים pesukim
their literal way is they can't allow for the possibility that the
fire might go that it might extinguish, okay, because if it's going
to extinguish, right, then you'll have violated this prohibition about whatever about
אש תמיד esh tamid and so on and for them even if
you didn't intend it, that will still be a violation. Okay, so
yes they say you go down the funnels, but they're concerned about
extinguishing the fire, I am not concerned about extinguishing the fire. So
two important points that emerge at this. Number one, the גמרא Gemara
has moved away from what it said before that even if you're
definitely going to extinguish it's not a problem because it's a מצוה,
mitzvah, right? Now the גמרא Gemara has actually said actually take all
of that back. The reason it's not a problem is you're an
אינו מתכוין. eino mitchaven. If the real answer was that it's a
מצוה mitzvah and that gets around the problem, then you're back to
the problem about why do these other why do these ברייתות baraitot
say that it goes down the funnels and not on the fire?
So we have to say you're right, forget that issue, the only
way to explain this is it's a question about אינו מתכוין. eino
mitchaven. They hold that it's a problem, they say don't put it
on the fire, I hold it's not a problem, I say put
it on the fire. The other question is, what happened to the
fact of פסיק רישא? psik reisha? The גמרא Gemara before was assuming
the fire will definitely go out. Here it's assuming that it's not
a פסיק רישא. psik reisha. So רש"י Rashi says well there are
scenarios that you could imagine that you do sprinkle it like very
little drops at a time and you know maybe they evaporate before
they hit the fire whatever so it's not necessarily a פסיק רישא
psik reisha and that's why we can say it's not a problem
because it's אינו מתכוין. eino mitchaven. So first of all that raises
interesting questions. Is רש"י Rashi saying now and is שמואל Shmuel saying
according to this that when you burn it on the fire you're
only allowed to do it little drops because if you do it
a lot it's going to be a פסיק רישא? psik reisha? Or
is he saying that once somehow the תורה Torah is allowing it
because it will be able to be done in certain cases you
know without it sort of being a without it being a פסיק
רישא psik reisha right? Without it being what did I say okay
without being without
well okay without it being a פסיק רישא psik reisha so now
it sort of becomes a blanket allowance like that becomes it all
becomes very complicated and the גמרא Gemara never mentions פסיק רישא. psik
reisha. Actually the simple reading of this גמרא Gemara is that that
may that even with a פסיק רישא psik reisha they're debating whether
אינו מתכוין eino mitchaven is a problem or not. The simple reading
of this גמרא Gemara is that שמואל Shmuel saying that for רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon that אינו מתכוין eino mitchaven is not a problem,
it's not a problem even if it's a פסיק רישא, psik reisha,
okay, because this גמרא Gemara doesn't even mention the פסיק רישא psik
reisha issue. So that's interesting in terms of their general debate. But
now we have moved away from the argument that it's not a
problem because of the מצוה. mitzvah. We've said the reason it wouldn't
be a problem is because our אינו מתכוין eino mitchaven and that
at the end of the day שמואל Shmuel says I'm able to
say that and put it on the fire and keep the פסוק
pasuk the simple
meaning. But according to those that hold like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
that אינו מתכוין eino mitchaven is a problem, that's what's pushing them
to say you can't put the יין yayin on the fire, you
gotta pour it down the funnel. Yeah.
And he doesn't want to say that those ברייתות baraitot that the
contrary in terms of just talking about regular יין yayin you know
that you put...
No, everybody knows that the... No it says no because it says
clear כדברי רבי עקיבא. k'divrei Rabbi Akiva. We're talking about רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva is the one that's מחדש mechadesh that יין yayin could
be a separate קרבן korban so it's very clear not that way.
Okay so the גמרא Gemara says like this...
Okay so למימרא דשמואל כרבי שמעון סבירא ליה? l'meimra de-Shmuel k'Rabbi Shimon
s'vira lei? Are you telling me שמואל Shmuel holds like רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon that holds that אינו מתכוין eino mitchaven is not a
problem? ואמר שמואל מכבין גחלת של מתכת ברשות הרבים בשביל שלא יזוקו
בה רבים. ve-amar Shmuel mechabin gachelet shel matechet birshut harabim bishvil shelo
yizoku ba rabim. If you have a metal ember in רשות הרבים,
reshut harabim, a piece of metal that is heated up as a
like a flame like you know it's red hot and somebody can
step on it and you know get injured, that's not סכנת נפשות
sakanat nefashot but it's a concern about נזק nezek of רבים rabim
you're allowed to right you're allowed to extinguish it on שבת. Shabbat.
Okay why? Because it's נזק nezek of רבים rabim not סכנת נפשות
sakanat nefashot but it's only a דרבנן. d'rabbanan. Why is it only
a דרבנן? d'rabbanan?
Because it's not on fire
well no actually it's actually interesting... Well no actually it's actually interesting,
it's
a metal ember it's not burning it's just hot right?
So the idea that you can have a גחלת של מתכת gachelet
shel matechet is actually important, guys give me a second, is actually
important because it is actually the whole question about do incandescent lights
halakhically count as fire? And the general assumption that they that they
do is because basically what that is is it's a גחלת של
מתכת gachelet shel matechet what you basically have is you have a
piece of metal that is heated up red hot so it gives
off light and heat, okay, and that it's consuming something as opposed
to something which is like you know an LED or like you
know a what's the thing that's just a gas... fluorescent or whatever
like which is not really like burning a material okay what... phosphorus?
What well okay but here... Exactly. Anyway, you're burning something like this
physical what do you call it, this physical piece of metal because
ultimately that metal gets consumed, that's when you have to get your
new incandescent light because it snaps the filament, okay? And that's considered
actually to be a fire. Who cares if you're burning metal or
who cares if you're burning like a piece of wood? Okay. So
that actually is why this whole גחלת של מתכת gachelet shel matechet
is very important in thinking about incandescent lights. However, although that is
true, if you extinguish a גחלת של מתכת, gachelet shel matechet, okay,
you actually have not violated כיבוי kibuy דאורייתא. de'oraita. Why have you
not violated כיבוי kibuy דאורייתא? de'oraita? Because כיבוי kibuy requires producing a
גחלת. gachelet. Like כיבוי kibuy is the classic כיבוי kibuy and this
is the principle of מלאכה שצריכה לגופה, melacha shetzricha legufa, right?
כיבוי kibuy normally is considered a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa because מלאכה שצריכה לגופה melacha shetzricha legufa means you want
the end result produces something, and you want the a classic מלאכה
melacha is defined as something that creates and produces something. And so
therefore what is created through the act of extinguishing? Nothing. You're getting
rid of a fire. What are you creating? Well, the only thing
you're creating is you've got a nice piece of charcoal. And you
know, you can go ahead and go to the store and buy
a bag of charcoal. Charcoal is actually a desired end product if
you're trying to create charcoal. So the only way that you can
actually that כיבוי kibuy is a biblical violation is when it produces
charcoal, okay? So therefore, you understand why? Because otherwise it's not producing
anything. So therefore when you extinguish a metal flame, a flame that's
based on a piece of metal, even if that's a fire in
the תורה, Torah, it's not a prohibition, a תורה Torah prohibition of
extinguishing because you haven't produced some new end result, some different end
product than you had before, okay? You just stopped the piece of
metal from continuing to burn. It's not like producing of charcoal. So
therefore שמואל Shmuel says, since it's never going to be a תורה
Torah violation, I will let you extinguish the metal thing on שבת
Shabbos because it's a rabbinic violation and therefore you're doing it to
protect the
רבים. rabbim. אבל, Aval, דף מ"ב עמוד א Daf Mem Beis Amud
Aleph says לא גחלת של עץ. lo gachelet shel etz. If it
is a wooden fire, based on a piece of, you know, something
burning, a wooden ember, then you cannot because then you actually have
done a תורה Torah violation because then you have produced a piece
of charcoal. So now, one minute, so now the גמרא Gemara
asks assuming that you want
it or not or regardless? That's what the גמרא's Gemara going to
say. So that's the basis of שמואל's Shmuel reasoning. But now the
גמרא Gemara says one minute, you said שמואל Shmuel holds like רבי
שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Well, guess what? רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי
יהודה Rabbi Yehuda have a different debate as well, not just about
אינו מתכוון, eino mitkaven, but about something called מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה,
melacha she'eina tzricha legufa, okay? ואי סלקא דעתך Ve'i salka daitach כרבי
שמעון סבירא ליה, k'Rabbi Shimon sevira lei, but if שמואל Shmuel holds
like רבי שמעון, Rabbi Shimon, why is the wood case a תורה
Torah violation? אפילו גחלת של עץ נמי, Afilu gachelet shel etz nami,
even if it is a wood charcoal, you know, a wood-based fire,
it is only a rabbinic violation. Why? Because the idea of מלאכה
שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is the following: the idea
of מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina tzricha legufa is that you
have to identify what is considered to be the product, the halachically
defined result of the מלאכה. melacha. Okay, so by extinguishing, we said
the result is creating an ember. All right, now that if that
is halachically defined as the as the classic end result of this
מלאכה, melacha, then if you are doing this מלאכה melacha to produce
a different end result, then it is a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה.
melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. It's not an אינו מתכוון. eino mitkaven. אינו
מתכוון Eino mitkaven was I wasn't even trying to to put out
the fire, I was just trying to put the wine on the
fire. I wasn't even trying to make a furrow, I was just
trying to get the bench to the other side of the flower
bed. Here you are trying to extinguish the fire but your your
goal of that is not to produce what הלכה halacha defines as
the point of the מלאכה. melacha. You're not trying to produce the
the ember, what you're trying to produce is just not a fire
that's going to hurt people. So that's called a מלאכה שאינה צריכה
לגופה. melacha she'eina tzricha legufa. You are doing the מלאכה melacha and
intentionally doing the מלאכה melacha but not for its own purpose, to
achieve something else that's not defined as the normal end result. A
good- another good example of a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa is you dig a hole because you're trying to get
dirt. So the מלאכה melacha of digging a hole is a מלאכה
melacha of בונה, boneh, you're constructing something. When I'm digging my hole
to get dirt, I would be just as happy to go ahead
and get that dirt and go to a beach and dig it
from the sand there or go to a sandbox if I had
an available beach or sandbox. I am not trying to create a
hole. I am trying to get dirt. So it's not like, "Whoops,
a hole got created." It's not
unintentional. It's intended that I'm making the hole but I don't care
and that's not my goal. That's a מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha
she'eina tzricha legufa, okay? So now the גמרא Gemara says it's clear
since שמואל's Shmuel got a problem with this wood-based fire and extinguishing
it, even though that's a classic מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, melacha she'eina
tzricha legufa, it's clear that for שמואל, Shmuel, he holds not like
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon that מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה's melacha she'eina tzricha
legufa a problem. But you said that he
holds exactly! Since when are these two things connected? The גמרא Gemara
says, בדבר שאינו מתכוין סבר לה כרבי שמעון. bidvar she'eino miskaven savar
lah k'Rabbi Shimon. Look, when it comes to unintending and it wasn't
what I was trying to accomplish all together, right, and I wasn't,
you know, I wasn't trying to extinguish it at all, I hold
like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. If it winds up extinguishing, hey, that's
not my responsibility. That's not my act. ובמלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה, uv'melacha
she'eina tzericha legufa, when I'm trying to extinguish, and I just am
doing it for a different purpose than is defined as the purpose
of the מלאכה. melacha. So in that case, סבר לה כרבי יהודה.
savar lah k'Rabbi Yehuda. Here, I hold like רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda.
These are not related concepts. Now תוספות Tosafot has, תוספות Tosafot sort
of says like, you know, what was the גמרא'ס הוה אמינא? Gemara's
hava amina? Of course these are different ideas. But you know,
the answer is, they're not so different. Because both of them are
basically saying we don't just look at the physical act of what
the מלאכה melacha did. We look at how are you defining that
act through your intention. So in one idea, it's like whether was
I trying to do the act at all, is it connected to
me, and that's defined by intention. The other thing is I was
trying to do it, but am I doing it for the right
purpose? So they're not exactly the same, obviously. And the other thing
that bothers תוספות Tosafot is that the מלאכה שאינה צריכה לגופה melacha
she'eina tzericha legufa is just a שבת Shabbos idea. אינו מתכוין eino
miskaven as we see by the fact that we're applying it to
extinguishing the fire on the מזבח Mizbeach is a כל התורה כולה
kol haTorah kulah principle. But nevertheless, it's not a crazy הוה אמינא
hava amina that I mean there's a, it happens, it is very
interesting that רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda debate
both points. That in both points רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is less
concerned with the role your intention has, and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
is more concerned with the role your intention has. So it's not
crazy to think that you might sort of one might if not
necessarily imply the other, but you to think that they would tend
to go together.
רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon was the more lenient one, no?
Did I just, yeah, that's why he cares about your intention. I
think you said, I think you reversed it. No, I said, I
don't think so, but I was saying רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda doesn't
care about your intention, which means that he's going to be more
strict, okay, whereas רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon cares about your intention and
if your intention therefore is not matching up, therefore you're off the
hook.
So my question is this, I mean the way you know I'd
originally envisioned this is with גחלת של מתכת gachelet shel matechet would
be a דרבנן. derabbanan. I just envisioned like this white-hot like, you
know, like let's say bar metal, let's, you know, like somehow just
gone into the street, right? And the reason why דרבנן derabbanan because
there's no actual fire. Why can't that, would that
be, no, but
would that be a דרבנן? derabbanan?
So what do you mean there's no fire? You mean because there's
no, it's not giving off light?
It's not, it's not flaming, it's just, would that be a דרבנן?
derabbanan? It's giving off light, it's not giving off heat, but it's
really not, it's really not extinguishing itself the way that a tungsten
light bulb is, right, because it's not hot enough. Tungsten light bulb
is thousands of degrees hotter than a typical piece of metal. Right,
but I think what
you're saying that it's not fire is because there's not like a
flame that exists separate.
Is that, would that be an issue?
But, okay, but if that's true, look, the general consensus is that
incandescent lights are fire. But if you say that for fire it's
not enough that it burns something and it's not enough that it
produces heat and light, but it also has to have a flame,
right, then fine, then your incandescent lights aren't fire, aren't fire either.
Okay, but I'm just telling you that there's a big נפקא מינא
nafka mina in הלכה halacha because we tend to treat on שבת
Shabbos questions relating to incandescent lights as דאורייתא. de'oraisa.
Well, we do, but what about the, you know, is that like
an extension?
No, anyway רש"י Rashi says that the issue about גחלת של מתכת,
gachelet shel matechet, so if you look at רש"י, Rashi, לאו בת
כיבוי היא. lav bat kibui hi. He doesn't say it's not fire.
He says you can't do כיבוי kibui because you don't produce a
גחלת. gachelet. Okay, so anyway.
So you're saying from the תורה Torah perspective, at least the way
גמרא'ס Gemara's taking it, it doesn't there doesn't necessarily need to be
a flame. Right. Well, so if I have like a white-hot whatever
it is and there's no fire at all, like you know I
took it away from the fire, but it's like really hot enough
that like it can burn somebody so to speak.
What's the it?
I have like I put something, something metal, metal rod in the
fire.
Right, I understand. If if it gives off heat and light, if
is it is it like giving off like is it No, no
light. Just really Okay, light is assumed to be a part of
it. So for example, when you get to questions on like יום
טוב Yom Tov and like you know where you're allowed to, you
know, can you, you know, like your your metal stove, right, can
you can you turn it or whatever and adjust the flame because
you can rise and lower gas stove, right, if it's not totally
extinguishing or whatever, I mean, whatever that's a separate question. But anyway,
but the the general assumption is is that if you're getting it
from non-red hot to red hot, that's a problem because then it's
like making a new fire. That once it actually is giving off
a glow, right, and giving off light, right, so your metal sort
of coil on your on your electric stove, imagine you turned off
all the lights in your place and you just had that metal
coil, you wouldn't get it wouldn't you wouldn't see any light from
it. But once it got red hot, it would give light into
the room. So the general assumption is it doesn't need a flame
but it needs to give off light. It needs to give off
heat and light. Okay, but yeah, that's a whole discussion. Yeah.
Yeah, remember חז"ל Chazal didn't know yet the difference between combustion and
simple heat versus light.
Yeah, but they could but they could react to the reality of
flame. Right. Well, anyway, alright, let's keep let's keep on going. Okay,
so אמר רב הונא Amar Rav Huna נסכים שנטמאו Nesachim shenitmu עושה
להן ose len
מערכה maaracha בפני עצמן bifnei atzman וסורפן. v'sorfan.
If you've got these wine or oils or these liquid things and
they that were supposed to be put on the fire whatever they
were supposed to be done with and they became טמא, tamei, you
burn them in the עזרה Azara because the הלכה halacha is the
irony is that remember when you had the פרים הנשרפים Parim Hanisrafim
like the קרבן korban that's supposed to have the blood brought in,
there the stuff gets burned outside of the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
But if you have something that becomes פסול pasul in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, you burn it in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
So he says the same is true about these things. So obviously
like why should it be different? So the חידוש chiddush is and
רש"י Rashi sort of tries to figure out why is this true?
That you make it separate fire. You don't burn it on the
standard fire for burning invalid things. רש"י Rashi thinks that the reason
to do this you could say the reason to do this is
what we just said before because this stuff will might extinguish the
other fire so you got to maybe I don't know handle it
specially. But anyway but רש"י Rashi says the point is is that
it's not as obvious that you're burning these liquids and for some
reason if you're burning פסול pasul things we want it to be
seen that what you're doing is burning this פסול pasul thing so
therefore if you're doing it burning it together with the fire that
you're burning פסול קרבנות pasul korbanot nobody sees that liquids are being
burned. So you want to have a special fire.
Okay, משום שנאמר mishum shene'emar בקודש באש תשרף Bakodesh Ba'esh Tisaref which
is the general principle that if something becomes invalid in the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash you burn it in the בית המקדש. Beis HaMikdash.
Okay, תניא נמי הכי Tanya nami hachi ויתצמו לי v'yitatsemu li הדם
והשמן והמנחות והנסכים שנטמאו hadam v'hashemen v'hamenachot v'hanesachim shenitmu all these liquids
blood and oil and actually the מנחה mincha that's interesting that's not
a liquid but maybe again it's not meat it's a little bit
more you know it's a little more you'll throw it on the
fire if you follow רש"י's Rashi point and it won't stay as
like a piece of meat burning on the fire you know it'll
all disperse or whatever and the נסכים שנטמאו עושה להם מערכה בפני
עצמן וסורפן. nesachim shenitmu ose len maaracha bifnei atzman v'sorfan. You make
their own fire and you burn that. אמר ליה Amar lei שמואל
Shmuel לרב חנה בגדתאה l'Rav Chana Bagdata'ah he said to רב חנה
Rav Chana from I guess Baghdad, אייתי לי בי עשרה aiti li
bei asara get me ten people together. Okay, sometimes you have these
statements, ואימא לכו קמייהו v'eima lachon kama'aihu and I want to teach
you in front of them I want to publicize this ruling it's
such an important ruling נסכים שנטמאו hanesachim shenitmu עושה להם מערכה בפני
עצמן וסורפן. ose len maaracha bifnei atzman v'sorfan. Very bizarre, right? Of
all the things you want to bother getting together ten people so
everybody knows this הלכה halacha it's this very obscure point which is
like you know not even such so radical. We all know you
burn stuff in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash that becomes פסול. pasul.
It's just the idea that they have a separate you know type
of a fire so it's very strange why he would sort of
make such a point about this of get me a מנין minyan
together I want to announce this in public. Anyway, הדרן עלך כל
התדיר. Hadran alach Kol HaTadir. Okay, so that is the end of
that פרק perek which was about precedent but in the end ended
ended with this whole thing about these various liquids that get offered
on. Yes.
It's very interesting mentioning Baghdad because it was actually formed in the
eighth century.
So so then maybe it isn't Baghdad.
Yeah well or it it might have been a place that was
just a village then. Yeah. So I mean it's obviously something something.
Okay, now we get on to דם חטאת Dam Chatas which is
a פרק perek which is about what it says it's about which
is the first words which is about special הלכות halachos about the
blood of a חטאת. chatas. Okay and here we're going to start
with an actual פסוק pasuk which says by the blood of a
חטאת chatas it says אשר יזה מדמה על הבגד asher yizeh midama
al habeged if the blood of a חטאת chatas gets splattered on
a garment תכבס במקום קדוש techaves bemakom kadosh you have to launder
the garment in a holy place because you know don't take the
garment outside of the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash there's a special הלכה
halacha of laundering the garment when blood of a of a חטאת
chatas gets splattered on it. Okay, so totally new discussion now. דם
חטאת שניתז על הבגד Dam chatas shenitaz al habeged you have the
blood was splattered on a garment הרי זה טעון כיבוס harei zeh
ta'un kibus so you have to launder it. Now this משנה mishnah
by the way is going to be a very מדרש הלכה midrash
halacha type of a משנה. mishnah. אף על פי שאין הכתוב מדבר
אלא בנאכלות Af al pi she'ein hakatuv medaber ela bene'achlot it's going
directly engage the פסוקים. psukim. Even though the פשט pshat of the
פסוקים psukim seems to be talking only about חטאות chata'os that are
eaten a classic
חטאת chatas שנאמר shene'emar במקום קדוש תאכל bimkom kadosh te'achel okay בחטאת
מועד יאכלו bechata mo'ed yochlu eat in a holy place and then
it goes on to say ואשר יזה מדמה על הבגד תכבס במקום
קדוש. v'asher yizeh midama al habeged techaves bemakom kadosh. Okay, so the
opening of the of the פסוקים psukim seem to be talking about
a normal חטאת chatas that was eaten. Even though that's true אחד
הנאכלות ואחד הפנימיות טעונות כיבוס echad hane'achlot v'echad hapnimiyot te'unot kibus whether
it is a חטאת chatas that eaten or whether it's an inner
חטאת chatas that is burned, the הלכה halacha is equally applies to
them even though the straight meaning of the פסוק pasuk is speaking
about only eaten חטאות. chata'os. שנאמר shene'emar תורת החטאת Torat HaChatas this
is the תורה Torah of the חטאת chatas תורה אחת לכל החטאות
Torah achat l'chol hachata'ot it applies to all חטאות. chata'os. Okay, that's
a very interesting little מדרש הלכה midrash halacha in a משנה. mishnah.
חטאת פסולה אין דמה טעון כיבוס. Chatas pesula ein dama ta'un kibus.
Now let's say you have a חטאת chatas that's invalid like נשחטה
שלא לשמה nishchata shelo lishma and the blood splattered on a garment.
There you don't have to launder the garment. Why? Because בין שהייתה
לו שעת הכושר bein shehayta lo sha'at hakesher whether because it says
אשר יזה מדמה על הבגד asher yizeh midama al habeged so and
so even though יזה yizeh is talking about it got splattered on
the garment we learn from that it's a חטאת chatas whose blood
deserves to be thrown, okay, deserves to be sprinkled. But if it's
a חטאת chatas that the blood is invalid and does not is
not does not deserve to be sprinkled then it doesn't. doesn't have
that power to have this make this problem with the clothes and
so on. Okay. So, בין שהיתה לשעת הכושר בין
שלא היתה לשעת הכושר, bein she-hayta lishas hachosher bein shelo hayta lishas
hachosher, and this idea that the blood does not demand laundering if
it is invalid is whether the חטאת chatas had a moment when
the blood was valid or from the very beginning the blood was
never valid. Or the חטאת chatas was never valid. איזהו שעת הכושר?
Eizehu she'as hachosher? What's a case where it initially was fit to
be thrown? שלנה Shelana if it slept overnight, so the blood was
caught in a כלי שרת, kli shares, it could have been thrown
and then you left it overnight. ושנטמאה Ushenitme'a became tamei. ושיצאה She-yatz'ah
and it was brought out of the or it was brought out
of the בית המקדש. Beis Hamikdash. ואיזוהי שלא היתה לה שעת הכושר,
Ve-eizohi shelo haysah lah she'as hachosher, what's blood that was never fit?
Okay. שנשחטה חוץ לזמנה, She-nishchitah chutz lizmanah, the חטאת chatas was shechted
once back to פיגול piggul again with the intent of the wrong
time, וחוץ למקומה Vechutz limkomah the wrong place, ושקיבלו פסולים את דמה
U-shekiblu pesulim es damah or invalid people
caught the blood or wasn't caught in a כלי שרת. kli shares.
All these types of things it was never fit. It doesn't matter
if it was never fit or once fit, if the blood right
now is not fit to be thrown then it does not have
this הלכה. halacha. Okay, now I'm not taking questions now because we
gotta move. Okay now, גמרא. Gemara. דם חטאת. Dam chatas. ואי תורה
אחת לכל חטאות, Ve-ee torah achas le-chol chatos, and if it's one
תורה torah for all חטאות, chatos, אפילו חטאת העוף נמי, afillu chatas
ha-of nami, so the גמרא Gemara asks on the משנה, Mishnah, wait,
if תורה אחת torah achas includes an inner חטאת chatas because it's
one story for all חטאות, chataos, then this הלכה halacha about the
blood sprinkling and laundering the garment should also be true about a
bird חטאת. chatas. אלמה תניא? Almah tanya? Why do we teach in
a ברייתא? Baraisa? יכול יהא דם חטאת העוף טעון כיבוס? Yachol yehei
dam chatas ha-of ta'un kibus? Maybe the blood of a bird חטאת
chatas should also have follow this הלכה halacha and you'd have to
launder it?
תלמוד לומר: זאת, talmud lomar zot, this. זאת Zos, is a limiting
word. Only the things we're talking about, not a broader scope of
things. So now we got a problem. We have an including word
תורה torah and a limiting word זאת. Zos And we're going to
have to figure out why we chose to include the inner חטאת
chatas and exclude the bird חטאת. chatas. Okay. Because the פסוקים psukim
are not giving us a hint to that, so we are going
to have to make the choice, we're going to have to include
one thing and exclude another. אמר ריש לקיש משום בר קפרא, Amar
Reish Lakish mishum Bar Kappara, אמר קרא. amar kra. Okay so that's
one answer, okay. So, אמר ריש לקיש, Amar Reish Lakish, so ריש
לקיש Reish Lakish has a different answer that makes it easier to
exclude a bird. אמר ריש לקיש משום בר קפרא, Amar Reish Lakish
mishum Bar Kappara, אמר קרא, amar kra, the verse says
תישחט במקום קדוש. tishachet bimkom kadosh. It says slaughter it, so you
see we're only talking about the things that are slaughtered, not birds.
בנשחטות הכתוב מדבר. Be-nishchatos haksav midaber. So the גמרא Gemara says no
no no, you can't do that. You can't say oh it's clear
we're only talking about non-birds because if we're looking at the פשט,
pshat, we're also talking about only things that are eaten and not
an inner חטאת. chatas. ואימא בנאכלות הכתוב מדבר Ve-eima be-ne'echalos haksav midaber
כדכתיב kedichsiv במקום קדוש תאכל? bimkom kadosh tei'achel? Or eat it in
a holy place. שבפנים לא. She-bifnim lo. Okay, so
פשט pshat of the פסוקים, psukim, it's limited to both things that
are eaten and to non-birds. But so you can't say there's no
basis to choose to include one and exclude the other because the
פשט pshat is we're limited to both. תורה Torah is including, זאת
Zos. is limiting. Okay, so you still have to tell me what
makes you include one and exclude the other. So the גמרא Gemara
says, רבתה רחמנא תורה. Ribah Rachmana torah. No, תורה torah allows us
to include the inner חטאות. chataos. אי הכי, Ee hachi, אפילו חטאת
העוף נמי? afillu chatas ha-of nami? So bird? No, מיעט רחמנא זאת.
Mi'et Rachmana zos. So we're back to square
one. Okay. ומה ראית? U-mah ra'isa? ומה ראית? U-mah ra'isa?
What leads you to say that? Meaning what is the basis of
saying that we're going to exclude birds and include inner חטאת? chatas?
You know that you have an including word and an excluding word.
You got the birds, you got the inner. What makes you make
the choice that you made? Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says, מסתברא
דחטאת בהמה פנימיות הוה ליה לרבויי. Mistabra de-chatas behemah pnimiyos havah leih
leribuyei. No no no. The, if we've got to include something, an
inner חטאת chatas has many many many more points of comparison to
an outer one than a bird חטאת chatas does. Okay. The פשט
pshat of the פסוק pasuk is the פסוק pasuk is talking about
outer חטאת. chatas. That's the פשט. pshat. That is eaten. Okay. It
says, right, תאכל tei'achel and that is a בהמה behemah because it
says, you know, תישחט. tishachet. Okay. That's the פשט pshat of the
פסוק. pasuk. So what is it more similar to? Is it more
similar to a bird
חטאת, chatas, this outer בהמה, behemah, or is it more similar to
an inner חטאת? chatas? So let's think about the points of comparison
and we're going to see that if we got to include something,
this is much more similar than the bird. Let's see why. Okay.
שכן בהמה. She-ken behemah. They're both בהמות. behemos. Okay. So this is
a בהמה behemah and this is a בהמה. behemah. Okay. That's one
point of comparison. שחיטה. Shechitah. Okay. So תישחט, tishachet, because they're בהמה,
behemah, you have a שחיטה shechitah here and you have a שחיטה
shechitah here.
צפון. Tzafon. They're both in the north. Right? A bird, okay, is
not a בהמה. behemah. A bird is an עוף, of, it’s not
שחיטה, shechita, it’s מליקה, melikah, it doesn’t need צפון, tzafon, it’s כל
מקום, kol makom, okay. This is צפון tzafon and צפון. tzafon.
Okay. וקבלת כלי, v'kabbalas keli, so you have כלי, kli, כלי, kli,
כלי kli and here you don’t have a כלי, kli, the bird,
the water, it goes like straight on the מזבח, mizbeiach, right, it
squirts straight on the מזבח mizbeiach without a
כלי. kli. Okay. וקרן וארבע ואצבע וחודה ואישים. v'keren v'arba v'etzba v'chuda
v'ishim. A lot of things. קרן, keren, the horn of the מזבח,
mizbeiach, whereas the bird חטאת chatas goes on the lower part of
the מזבח. mizbeiach.
This is good review.
Yeah, exactly. Okay, וחודה, v'chuda, okay, חודה chuda is the, I mean
that’s a little bit of a cheat because that’s just a subset
of קרן. keren. Where does it go on the horn? On the
edge of the horn. Okay, so ואישים, v'ishim, and this you put
the entrails because it’s a בהמה behemah on the אש, eish, entrails
on the אש, eish, whereas here it’s all eaten. Okay, you put
nothing on the fire, all eaten, no אש. eish. Okay, so one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven. Seven or six or seven ways
in which it’s similar to this and different from that. If we’ve
got to include something, we’re including the inner חטאת. chatas. The only
difference is this has the blood on the inside and isn’t eaten.
One point of difference. Everything else is the same. So the גמרא
Gemara says אדרבה, aderaba, let me say the opposite. חטאת עוף chatas
of should be included. Here the points of comparison of this with
the bird חטאת. chatas. What’s comparison? שכן חוץ, sheken chutz,
the blood goes on the outside כמוה kamosa and אכילה achilah כמוה,
kamosa, they’re both eaten. So the גמרא Gemara says that is no
competition, it’s you know two against seven, no contest I should say.
הנך נפישת, hanoch nefishet, excuse me, many many more points of comparison.
There’s a reason we’re going to include this and exclude the birds.
Okay. רב יוסף אמר אמר קרא, Rav Yosef amar amar kra, רב
יוסף Rav Yosef says the פסוק pasuk says יאכלנה. yochlena.
Okay, it says the פסוק pasuk says you know במקום קדוש יאכלנה,
bimakom kadosh yochlena, I think is the פסוק, pasuk, you shall eat
it. לזו ולא לאחרת, ונאכלות מיעט הכתוב. lazu v'lo l'acheres b'ne’echalos mi'at
hakasuv. So it actually says interesting because it says יאכלנה, yochlena, you’ll
eat it, right, that’s how we know that it’s talking about
we know it’s talking about an eaten חטאת. chatas. And then you
have the word זאת, Zos we’re saying זאת zos, is saying in
the scope of what we’re talking about, things that are eaten, okay,
there we’re going to exclude certain things. We’re going to exclude other
חטאות chata'os that are eaten. So יאכלנה yochlena is basically coming and
focusing us on that it’s within the things that are being eaten,
that’s where we’re going to exclude something, we’re going to exclude the
bird. לזו ולא לאחרת lazu v'lo l'acheres, ונאכלות מיעט הכתוב. v'ne’echalos mi'at
hakasuv. Okay, so it’s not the זאת zos that excludes it, it’s
the יאכלנה. yochlena. Okay, that יאכלנה yochlena saying amongst the things that
are eaten, we’re only talking about one of the things that are
eaten. So we’re going to exclude another חטאת chatas that’s eaten, we’re
going to exclude the bird חטאת. chatas. That’s how we’re going to
learn it out. ואלא זאת למה לי? ve’ela zos lama li? That’s
true, why do you need זאת? zos Just learn it from יאכלנה
yochlena that we’re excluding a particular חטאת chatas that’s eaten, the bird
חטאת. chatas. אילב זאת, ilav zos, if it weren’t for that הוה
אמינא, hava amina, I would have said
יאכלנה yochlena אורחיה דקרא. orchay d'kra. No, יאכלנה yochlena isn’t meant to
exclude, it’s just a way we’re talking about it. So we say
eat it, right, now we don’t just say eat, we say eat
it. קא משמע לן kamashma lan that the זאת zos? is telling
something is being excluded, but the יאכלנה yochlena focuses us in and
say what we’re excluding is something that would be eaten. So we’re
excluding a bird חטאת. chatas. Okay. רבא אמר אמר קרא. Rava amar
amar kra. So that’s one way. רבא’s Rava going to say something
that’s going to sort of start in a different direction and it’s
going to end up in close to the same place. אמר קרא,
amar kra, no no no. I’m going to, you’re sort of assuming
that the פסוק pasuk is talking about an outer חטאת, chatas, we’re
going to include an inner and we’re going to exclude a bird.
But that this is where, this is our starting point. Okay, this.
And then we’re going to include this, right, and we’re going to
exclude this. Okay. רבא’s Rava saying I’m going to start different. I’m
going to say the פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk of this
הלכה halacha of wandering, this goes against the משנה Mishna and the
גמרא’s Gemara going to do somersaults to make it fit in the
משנה. Mishna. The פשט pshat of the פסוק pasuk that we’re talking
about wandering starts with an inner חטאת. chatas. Okay, it does not
start with an outer חטאת. chatas. Okay, and then we’re going to
include this way. We’re not starting here, we’re starting here. Let’s take
a look.
אשר יזה, asher yizeh, when it speaks about the blood being splattered,
right, on a garment, it says that it’s splattered, בהזאה הכתוב מדבר.
b'haza'ah hakasuv medaber. Which blood is splattered? Not the blood of an
outer חטאת. chatas. The blood of an outer חטאת chatas is placed
with a finger on the on the on the horn, oh I
forgot to mention finger by the points of comparison, whereas the inner...
חטאת, Chatas, that's where you're doing the splattering, right? אחת אחת ואחת.
Achat achat ve'achat. I mean it's also a finger but it's a
splattering or a or a spraying or whatever, you know. So so
so
since it speaks about going on the garment and it uses the
key verb of הזאה, Hazaa, that is a word that is meaningful
primarily about an inner חטאת. Chatas. So our fundamental הלכה halacha starts
with an inner
חטאת. Chatas. Okay. בהזאות הכתוב מדבר. Behazaot hakatuv medaber. So גמרא Gemara
says one minute. והתנן Vehatnan our משנה Mishnah says, אף על פי
כן הכתוב מדבר בנאכלות. Af al pi ken hakatuv medaber benechalot. That's
not the משנה. Mishnah. The משנה Mishnah says פשט pshat is that
we're talking about eaten קרבנות, korbanot, okay. And then we're gonna broaden
it to exclude the inner ones. You're starting with the inner ones.
אף על פי שאין הכתוב אלא בנאכלות. Af al pi she'en hakatuv
ela benechalot. גמרא Gemara says no. So רבא Rava says back, לעניין
מריקה ושטיפה. le'inyan merika ushtifa. No, no, no. What the משנה Mishnah
means is because there's something else mentioned in the פסוק pasuk which
we're going to get to, that when you cook the חטאת Chatas
in a pot, you have a whole process of cleansing the pot
of hot water and cold water and the whole thing. So רבא's
Rava saying is read the משנה Mishnah to say is the following:
although the first part of the פסוקים psukim is talking about an
eaten חטאת Chatas when it's dealing with the cooking in the pot,
this is what he's reading into the משנה. Mishnah. When we get
around to talking about the splattering and we use the verb הזאה,
Hazaa, at that stage we're talking about an inner חטאת. Chatas. Okay?
You got it? So rather than saying the whole thing, both about
the cooking and the splattering is the outer, no. When you're talking
about the eating and the cooking, that's the outer. When you talk
about the splattering and you use the word הזאה, Hazaa, then you're
talking about the inner. Okay.
So והתניא אף
על פי שאין הכתוב מדבר אלא בנאכלות. vehatanya af pi she'en hakatuv
medaber ela benechalot. No, לעניין מריקה ושטיפה. le'inyan merika ushtifa. אבל לעניין
כיבוס אשר יזה כתיב בו, Aval le'inyan kibus asher yuzeh ktiv bo,
but regarding when the פסוקים psukim get to talking about the splattering
issue, then the point of departure is the inner חטאת. Chatas. אי
הכי Ihachi says the גמרא, Gemara, אחד הנאכלות ואחד הפנימיות. echad hanechalot
ve'echad hapnimiyot. When it's saying it includes both things that are eaten
and things that are inner חטאות, chataot, according to you, it should
have reversed the order. The point of departure is the inner חטאת.
Chatas. It should have said אחד הפנימיות ואחד הנאכלות מיבעי ליה. echad
hapnimiyot ve'echad hanechalot mibaya lei. It should have said whether it's an
inner חטאת Chatas or an eaten חטאת Chatas because according to you
the point of departure is the inner חטאת. Chatas. גמרא Gemara says
fine, switch the גרסא. girsa. תני אחד הפנימיות ואחד הנאכלות. Tani echad
hapnimiyot ve'echad hanechalot. Fine, edit the text. Okay. אי הכי Ihachi says
the גמרא, Gemara, חטאת העוף נמי? Chatat of nami? Okay, if we're
starting here and then we're somehow going to include this from the
word תורת, Torat, why don't we also include the bird חטאת? Chatas?
So now we're going to get back to everything we said before.
So רבא's Rava approach isn't going to solve anything because we're still
going to have to explain why include an outer one and exclude
the bird. מי איכא רחמנא זאת. Mi-ika rachmana zot. No, זאת zos
excludes. אי הכי Ihachi חיצונית נמי? chitzona nami?
Let's exclude an outer חטאת. Chatas. לא נמי לא. Lo nami lo.
ריבה רחמנא תורת. Ribah rachmana Torat.
ומה ראית? U-mah raita? So what makes you include an outer חטאת
Chatas and not a bird? מסתברא חטאת בהמה הוה ליה לרבויי. Mistabra
Chatat behema hava lei leribuye. Guess what? It's got all these points
of comparison. שכן בהמה שחיטה צפון קבלת כלי וקרן ואצבע וכולי ואישי.
She-ken behema shechita tzafon kabbalat kli vekeren ve'etzba vechulei ve'ishi. Okay.
Now we've got a harder thing. It's now he I mean not
harder, whatever, I mean it's good that it's harder. But what how
is it compared to a bird חטאת, Chatas, right? If we're starting
from the inner one, right, the comparison to a bird חטאת Chatas
was that it was eaten. Okay and that they were outer. Here
there's like no comparisons to a bird חטאת. Chatas. An inner חטאת
Chatas isn't eaten and it isn't outer. Okay. So let's see what
the גמרא Gemara says. אדרבה
חטאת העוף הוה ליה לרבויי. Adderaba Chatat Of hava lei leribuye. Why?
שכן הזאה כמותה. She-ken hazaa kemota. אה! Ah! That now actually it's
even a stronger question. Because you רבה, Rabba, רבא, Rava, was it
רבא Rava or רבה? Rabba?
רבא. Rava. You started with the word אשר יזה. Asher yuzeh. And
you said the word אשר יזה Asher yuzeh is an inner חטאת
Chatas word because of the blood is splattered and it's not placed
with a finger. Guess what? You know what other blood is squirted
and not placed with a finger and splattered? The bird. So that's
even a stronger question. It's true there's a lot more points of
comparison, but you were this was your focus, the words אשר יזה.
Asher yuzeh. So that should come and include the bird. So the
גמרא Gemara gives the same answer as it gave before. The גמרא
Gemara says הני נפישן. hani nefishen. Nevertheless these are more points of
comparison. So like what did רבא Rava accomplish? He didn't accomplish anything.
At the end of the day we make this comparison because there're
more points of comparison. So why do you have to twist it
around and say we start here and go this way and that
makes the bird question a stronger question, right? So just go by
the simple sense of the משנה. Mishnah. You start here and again
these are the more points of comparison so we're going to include
an inner חטאת Chatas and we're not going to include a bird.
Fine. I have no idea. That was not a like a rhetorical
question. Well that was I guess a rhetorical question. It was not
a question I had an answer to. Okay.
All right. Now we're going to move on. בעי רב אבין, Bai
Rav Avin, רב אבין Rav Avin asked the following question. חטאת העוף
שהכניס דמה בפנים מה? Chatat of she-hichnis dama bifnim mah? This is
going to be a fun question. It's not exactly our case about
the splattering and the laundry.
Okay. We taught earlier if you bring the blood of a חטאת,
hatat, an outer חטאת hatat into the היכל, heikhal, right? So then
it invalidates the חטאת hatat and you have to burn it and
the whole thing. Normally you're bringing it in with a כלי. kli.
What if you do מליקה melikha on a bird, on a bird
חטאת, hatat, and you put your hand against the throat so you're
not letting it squirt, and then you walk it in like that
into the היכל. heikhal. Is it like bringing the blood in with
its כלי kli into the היכל, heikhal, or do we say as
long as it's still in the throat and it hasn't come out
of the animal, you're not really relating to it yet as blood
and so on, and therefore it does not invalidate the חטאת? hatat?
Okay, that's the question. חטאת עוף שהכניס דמה בצוארו בפנים מהו? Hatat
ohf she-hikhnis dama b'tzavaro bifnim mahu? What do you say? סבר ככלי
שרת דמי? Savar kikli sharet dami? Since there's no כלי שרת kli
sharet by the bird, its actual neck is the כלי שרת, kli
sharet, it's its container right now, okay? So therefore ומיפסל umipsal and
it becomes invalidated. או דילמא כצואר בהמה מדמי? O dilma k'tzavar beheima
midamei? Or maybe you should compare it to the neck of a
בהמה. beheima. If you slaughtered a בהמה beheima and put your hand
against its neck, and you'd need a very big hand I guess
or whatever, and walked it into the עזרה, azara, into the היכל
heikhal and walked it out, you would not invalidate. We say that's
just still part of the בהמה. beheima. So maybe we should say
it's not in a כלי kli that's being now brought up as
a process of being offered up, right? But that's for obvious reason
because a בהמה beheima the blood goes in a כלי. kli. So
this thing, you know, if you look at it from the perspective
of the physical animal, nothing has come out yet, it's like a
בהמה beheima and so on. On the other hand, you recognize that
there's normally no כלי kli here, maybe this is already considered like
it's in the כלי kli and it should invalidate. Okay, so the
גמרא Gemara says
so what's the answer? אמר רחמנא, Amar Rachmana, I'm sorry, כצואר בהמה,
k'tzavar beheima, I misread that line before. כצואר בהמה, k'tzavar beheima, מדמה
אמר רחמנא. Midama amar Rachmana. It says that its blood is brought
inside
ולא בשרה, v'lo b'sara, and not its flesh. So if it's still
in the flesh, you're not bringing the blood as a separate entity
inside. In the same way we would say that by a cow
or a sheep, we'll say that by the bird. So תא שמע,
ta shema, come and hear. פרכסה ונכנסה לפנים וחזרה כשרה. Pirkesa v'nikhnesa
lifnim v'hazra kesheira. You went ahead, there's a ברייתא braita that says
you went ahead and you did מליקה melikha on your bird, and
then your bird thrashed around a bit because it was dying and
it rolled into the היכל heikhal and then it rolled out, it's
still כשרה. kesheira. Okay, it did not become invalid because the blood
went into the היכל. heikhal. Now the גמרא Gemara says that's because
it did it by itself, and part of the requirement that the
blood invalidates the חטאת hatat when it is brought inside is that
you're bringing it in לכפר, l'khaper, that you're intentionally bringing it in
for the purpose of atonement. So the implication here is that the
reason it doesn't invalidate is it wasn't intentionally brought in. But it
sounds like if you intentionally brought it in it would invalidate. Okay.
So הא הכניסה, ha hikhnesa, if you did it intentionally פסולה, psula,
it sounds like it would invalidate. So that's exactly your case. So
the גמרא Gemara says no, no, no. ולטעמיך אבקדשי קדשים דקתני, Uletameikh
ab'kodshei kodashim d'katani, no, because we taught something very similar by an
animal as well. What do we teach by like a חטאת hatat
or whatever? פרכסה ויצאה לדרום. Pirkesa v'yatza l'darom. We said let's say
the animal thrashed around, you slaughtered it in the north and it
thrashed around and moved itself into the south. וחזרה, V'hazra, and then
it came back into the north. כשרה, Kesheira, it's כשרה. kesheira. So
should I infer from this that if you intentionally moved the blood
to the south and brought it to the north it's invalid? That's
obviously not true. There's no invalidity. You have to שחט shekhet it
in the north, you don't invalidate the blood by bringing it to
the south. הא הוציאה פסולה? Ha hotzia psula? Should I therefore infer
from this that if you brought the blood to the south you
invalidate? That's obviously not true. So when it says it thrashed around
and did it by itself, it doesn't mean that if you intentionally
did it you would invalidate. So if that's true why did it
give the scenario of thrashing around if it's the same הלכה halakha
if it's intentional or not intentional? Because it's not contrasting it to
the same thing where you did it intentionally. What it's contrasting it
is when it thrashed around and went outside the עזרה. azara. And
there the חידוש hidush is even though you didn't bring it outside
the עזרה, azara, even though it brought itself out of the עזרה,
azara, that doesn't invalidate it. Okay.
אלא האי יצתה לחוץ אצטריכא ליה. Ela hai yatzta l'chutz itztrikha lei.
The point isn't to say if you intentionally bring the blood inside
the neck of the animal in, you invalidate. That's not true. I
could say you don't invalidate even if you brought the blood in
while it was in the neck. The reason it gave the scenario
of thrashing was to tell you because if it thrashed outside of
the עזרה azara and it moved itself outside the עזרה, azara, even
though you didn't do it and it did it by itself, it
still invalidates. הכא נמי יצתה אצטריכא ליה. Hakha nami yatzta itztrikha lei.
Okay, so we don't know the answer, we don't know the answer
of whether you bring the blood while it hasn't left the neck
yet by a bird is that considered like blood in a כלי
שרת kli sharet that would actually invalidate it if you brought it
in to the היכל. heikhal. We don't know the answer. Okay. Let's
stop. Okay, let's do one more line here. בעי רבי אבין, Bei
Rabi Avin, רבי אבין Rabi Avin asked: נשפך על הרצפה ואספה מהו?
Nishpach al
haritzpah ve-asafah mahu? Okay, let's say the blood squirted, you know, that
you were it was going to go squirt out onto the מזבח,
Mizbe'ach, but you missed. Somebody distracted you, said, "What?" and it all
now squirted out onto the floor. Can you gather it up from
the floor and now throw it on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, the blood
of a bird? Okay, again, we're not yet talking about the issue,
the blood of a bird, right. We're not yet talking about the
issue about laundering, okay? So,
so what's the הלכה? halacha? Do you remember the הלכה halacha about
if you spilled the blood of an animal, of like a cow?
If you caught it in a כלי שרת kli sharet and spilled
it, you can gather it up. If you didn't catch it at
all in a כלי שרת, kli sharet, you can't gather it up,
okay?
So here, but a bird
doesn't have a כלי שרת. kli sharet. So is it as soon
as you slaughter it, again, it's a similar question, the body of
the bird is like a כלי שרת kli sharet and it's like
been caught in the כלי שרת kli sharet and now it's ready
to be thrown and if it gets spilled, pick it up? Or
is it actually saying there's no כלי שרת kli sharet and if
you don't squirt it directly on the
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, that's not the מצווה, mitzvah, okay? So, מהו? mahu? אצרוכי
הוא דלא אצרוכי רחמנא כלי שרת? Atzruchei hu delo atzruchei Rachmana kli
sharet? The Torah says you don't need a כלי שרת, kli sharet,
but it's not telling you that the מצווה mitzvah is it has
to go straight from the neck of the בהמה behemah onto the
מזבח. Mizbe'ach. It's basically says you don't need a כלי שרת kli
sharet and maybe another way of saying this is and the body
of the bird itself counts as a כלי שרת kli sharet if
you want to connect it to the previous question, okay? But it
doesn't have to go straight from the neck onto the מזבח, Mizbe'ach,
and therefore הלכך אוספו וכשר, hilkach osfo vekasher, gather it up off
the floor and use it, it's כשר. kosher. או דילמא, O dilma,
or do we say מפסל פסיל ביה רחמנא כלי שרת? mifsil pasil
bei Rachmana kli sharet? That the Torah is actually saying no, it
would invalidate it to use a כלי שרת kli sharet because the
הלכה halacha is it has to go straight from the neck to
the altar. Like you could have even said the question is let's
say I wanted to, I took the neck of my bird and
I put a כלי שרת kli sharet here, I had it squirt
into the כלי שרת kli sharet and then I threw it from
the כלי שרת kli sharet onto the altar. Exact same question. Is
the Torah saying like we're okay with a כלי שרת, kli sharet,
we just don't need it, okay? And therefore you want to use
a כלי שרת kli sharet or maybe you know the bird itself
is a כלי שרת, kli sharet, if it spilled, pick it up.
Or, that's one way, or the second way I think is more
what we would have assumed, the Torah's telling you no, this is
exactly the way it gets put on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, from the
neck of the bird, straight squirting on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, anything else
is not the
מצווה, mitzvah, okay? אמר רבא תא שמע, Amar Rava ta shema, come
and hear: יכול
יהא דם חטאת העוף טעון כיבוס? yakhol yehei dam chatat of taun
kibus? Going back to this issue about the bird, maybe the blood
of the bird has to be laundered, so תלמוד לומר Talmud lomar:
זאת, zot okay? That's why we know to exclude. But he says
one minute, אי סלקא דעתך מפסל פסיל ביה רחמנא, i salka daatakh
mifsil pasil bei Rachmana, if when the blood doesn't go straight on
the altar, it becomes invalid, remember, you know what thing does not
require laundering? פסול pasul blood. Remember that point? So why did we
need to exclude the blood of the bird? We could have excluded
it just by virtue of the fact that it's פסול pasul blood.
If it hits the garment and it's not going straight on the
מזבח, Mizbe'ach, it's already פסול. pasul. You got the point? So it
should that you know the laws of laundering don't apply based on
if if it's true that it's פסול pasul when it doesn't go
straight on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, you should you don't need to exclude
it because it's a bird. You should know the laws of laundering
don't apply because it becomes פסול pasul if it's not going straight
on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, okay? תיפוק ליה דאיפסיל ליה באויר כלי, Teipokei
lei de-ifsilei ba-avir kli, as soon as it goes over the air
space of the vessel that it's going to hit, okay, it's already
considered in the vessel and it's already פסול pasul before it hits
the vessel. It's just going over the air space and before it
hits the vessel it already is like it's been caught in a
different vessel and that should invalidate it according to this. And the
fact that that's not enough to exclude it, you need to exclude
it by virtue of it being a bird, shows me that this
does not invalidate. Okay, so that's his argument. So גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רב הונא בריה דרב יהושע: Amar Rav Huna berei de-Rav Yehoshua:
no, במדביע כלי בצוארה. bemadbi'a kli betzavara. No,
no, no. Here the case is it didn't go over the air
space. It went, like imagine you held the vessel like vertically, right,
and it just hit the side of the מזבח Mizbe'ach straight, hit
the side of the vessel or of your of your clothes straight,
it didn't go over any air space. So if it didn't go
over any air space, yes, it becomes פסול pasul when it hits
your clothes, but it didn't become פסול pasul beforehand. The הלכה halacha
that פסול pasul blood does not require cleansing is a הלכה halacha
that if it was פסול pasul before it hit your garment. If
it became פסול pasul only at the moment it hit your garment,
so the split second before it was still כשר kosher blood,
so
then it does actually require cleansing. So it could be that after
it hits the garment it becomes invalid because it has to go
straight on the מזבח, Mizbe'ach, but before it hit the garment it
was not invalid and therefore we had to exclude it by virtue
of it being blood of the bird. So we still don't know
the answer to this question whether what is the story? Does it
is the Torah telling me straight from the neck to the מזבח
Mizbe'ach or is the Torah telling me no, throw it on the
מזבח Mizbe'ach however you want, we're making it convenient for you, we're
telling you you know you could just go straight. But if you
want to catch it in a כלי שרת Klei Shares or whatever,
be my guest. Okay, obviously, the assumption is that no, it has
to go straight, but anyway, that's our question. And therefore, that would
have that נפקא מינה Nafka Mina if it spilled, if you caught
it in a כלי שרת, Klei Shares, could you still throw the
blood of a bird? And we don't have an answer yet. Okay,
so we will pick up